Guide to the Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History collection 2010.020
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Porter, Evangeline, 2010 March 3; 2010.020.036
  Born in North Carolina in 1932 and raised there by her grandmother, Evangeline "Eve" Porter came to Brooklyn in 1953. She married at that time and lived on Sterling Street. In 1973, she moved to her own apartment on St. Charles Place. Eve Porter attended Howard University and graduated from the College of New Rochelle's School of New Resources in Brooklyn. She volunteered at her children's school, and later worked as a paraprofessional at Paul Robeson High School. Porter was a toll collector and a Passenger Service Agent at John F. Kennedy Airport; both under the aegis of the Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority. She also worked as a guide for builders at the construction site of the North Tower at the World Trade Center. She has been a leader of the Crow Hill Community Association for decades, oversaw an offshoot organization in 1999 called the Franklin Avenue Commercial Revitalization Project, and acted as the secretary of the 77th Precinct Community Council.
  In the interview, Evangeline "Eve" Porter recalls moving to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. She makes some pointed comments about the growth of the West Indian Carnival on Labor Day weekends. Eve Porter remembers her personal challenges with neighborhood blight in the 1970s and '80s and the stands she had to take. She speaks generally about forming a block association and doesn't refer to the Crow Hill Community Association by name. Porter makes a prediction about the neighborhood changes in 2020 to 2025. She laments the steep hikes in rent for business owners and shares an anecdote about prompting Assemblyman Roger Green to raise $250,000 for the association to make improvements in the neighborhood. She says a few final words about community involvement in general and how activism can thrive with young people's involvement. Interview conducted by Treverlyn Dehaarte, Floyya Richardson, Monica Parfait, and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; North Carolina; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Rent |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crow Hill Community Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Green, Roger L. (Roger Leon); Porter, Evangeline; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Siegel, Stefanie, 2010 April 19; 2010.020.037
  Stefanie Siegel was born in Worcester, Massachusetts in 1951. She attended high school in Maryland, and after a decade of working and searching for the right opportunities, she attended Reed College in Portland, Oregon. She also has degrees from the University of Chicago and the City University of New York. Siegel began teaching English in the New York City Public School System in 1987. After teaching at Brooklyn's Erasmus Hall High School for a time, she began teaching at Paul Robeson High School in 1991. In addition to teaching there, she was the Coordinator of Student Affairs/Senior Advisor and joined a student-led group organized to save the school from permanent closure. Siegel founded Bailey's Cafe in 2002. The organization, which she also heads as Executive Director, is built on a doctrine of intergenerational learning. After a fundraising campaign, the non-profit moved to a permanent home at 324 Malcolm X Boulevard in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in 2015.
  Stefanie Siegel begins her interview by describing the work of Dr. Marcia Lyles, a principal at Paul Robeson High School in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. Dr. Lyles is credited with transforming the school, and Siegel contrasts it with her prior experience as a teacher at Erasmus Hall High School in Brooklyn's Flatbush neighborhood. Siegel looks at the larger picture of Robeson High's challenges to remain open to students during the Mayoral administration's attempts to phase out and consolidate some school districts. She talks about the changes she's seen over two decades in Crown Heights. Siegel describes the extracurricular efforts to engage students in intergenerational learning. This takes the form of a community organization named Bailey's Cafe. She advises students on how to prepare for senior year and how to be involved with their school and set standards for peers. She recalls her experience as a high school and college student; and how the latter prepared her to lead Bailey's Café. Interview conducted by Floyya Richardson, Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education, Higher |z New York (State) |z New York; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Haitians |z New York (State) |z New York; Intergenerational relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Erasmus Hall High School; New York (N.Y.). Department of Education; Paul Robeson High School (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Rosenbaum, Yankel; Siegel, Stefanie
- Simon, Cecil, 2010 March 24; 2010.020.038
  Cecil Simon was born in Guyana in 1961. He arrived in Brooklyn, with six siblings and his mother, in 1975 and lived on Carroll Street and Franklin Avenue in the Crown Heights neighborhood. Simon attended Paul Robeson High School when it was still named after Alexander Hamilton. After serving a twenty year jail sentence, he returned to Brooklyn. He was unemployed and living at Park Place and Nostrand Avenue as of 2010.
  In the interview, Cecil Simon speaks about moving to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights from Guyana. Later, he returns to the topic of immigration in relation to friction with other nationalities and challenges with job placement. Simon has some knowledge about the gangs operating in Brooklyn in the late 1970s and discusses how they affected his high school years. He reflects on his time at Alexander Hamilton High School and in general, appreciates the differences in teenagers then and now. He makes his observations of the changing demographics of Crown Heights. Simon speaks about his personal role model, his older brother. He also shares lessons that life has taught him, advises teenagers of this era and ends on a quote from Langston Hughes. Interview conducted by Monica Parfait, Ansie Montilus, Quanaisha Phillips, and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Courtesy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Guyana; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Hughes, Langston; Paul Robeson High School (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Simon, Cecil
- Staton, Meredith, 2010 April 7; 2010.020.039
  Meredith Staton was born in Germantown, Pennsylvania in 1938. He moved to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights in his twenties. Staton served his country in the Vietnam War and as a United States Postal Service employee at home. He has been the Captain of the Auxiliary Police Unit for the 77th Precinct and served on Community Board Eight. He is a proponent of securing landmark status for features of the neighborhood and was vocal in how the community reacted to the Atlantic Yards project and how Crown Heights was redistricted. Statton is a husband and father, as well.
  Meredith Staton begins the interview with a brief, recent history of the Crown Heights neighborhood in Brooklyn, starting in the late 1800s. He points out the shift in the local demographics into what he calls an "integrated neighborhood." He speaks at length on community involvement by way of his volunteer position as Auxiliary Captain for the 77th Precinct of the New York Police Department. Staton explains the redistricting of Crown Heights into North and South. He discusses his feelings on war in general when prompted to talk about his service time in Vietnam. Staton focuses on the importance of education and resourcefulness of this era's urban youth, and urges them to understand the history of subjugation and segregation for African Americans and immigrants of color. He briefly recalls the historic events of Nelson Mandela's visit to Crown Heights in 1990 and the factors of the 1991 riot and his role in terms of security. Interview conducted by Floyya Richardson, Treverlyn Dehaarte, and Alex Kelly.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Museums |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race identity; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Children's Museum; Cato, Gavin; City University of New York. Medgar Evers College; Community Board No. 8 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Mandela, Nelson; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History; Staton, Meredith
- Sutton, Sandra, 2010 April 5; 2010.020.040
  Sandra Sutton was born and raised in a small town in North Carolina. She attended high school and college in the state, as well. One of several children, she came to Brooklyn with sisters in the mid-1980s while her brothers went into the armed services. While living with a sister in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights, she married at age thirty and purchased a home nearby. Taking her husband's name, Gibbs, she taught at P.S. 41 in Brooklyn's Brownsville neighborhood. The couple didn't have children and divorced after ten years. After some library experience during her eighteen years of teaching, Sutton studied Library Science at Pratt Institute and received her master's degree. She was hired by Brooklyn Public Library and worked at the Eastern Parkway branch at the time of the interview in 2010. In 2015, she was a Neighborhood Library Supervisor at the Red Hook branch.
  Sandra Sutton offers some basic information about her history in North Carolina, moving to Brooklyn, getting married and divorced, and settling in the Crown Heights neighborhood. She reflects on the changing demographic of homeowners around her home and how it has left her feeling less connected to her community. She talks about her teaching career, regrets in life, and offers advice to young people. She describes the process that she went through to become a librarian and champions libraries in general and her workplace in particular, the Eastern Parkway branch of the Brooklyn Public Library. Sutton reflects on the contrasts between her youth in North Carolina and her adult life in Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Monica Parfait and Alex Kelly.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Librarians |z New York (State) |z New York; Libraries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; North Carolina; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Public Library; New York (N.Y.). Department of Education; Sutton, Sandra
- Taylor, Robert, 2010 April 1; 2010.020.041
  Robert Taylor was born in a small town in Texas in 1939. He graduated high school in 1964 and by that time had already held odd jobs as a gardener and paperboy and worked at a shoe store, a nursing home, a drug store and a bowling alley. Taylor was drafted into the military, trained in Louisiana and learned radio/TV repair, fought and was captured for a time in Vietnam, and served on a base in California. After his service, he worked for several years as a station porter for the New York City Transit Authority, as a shipping/receiving clerk in a hospital, and for the United States Postal Service. When he moved to Brooklyn's Crown Heights neighborhood in the 1970s, Taylor's first apartment was a shared studio. One of his roommates became his wife, and they moved to their own apartment in the Flatbush neighborhood. Taylor frequented the jazz nightclub Blue Coronet (1965 - 1985) in Bedford-Stuyvesant and other bars, and alcoholism took a toll and ended his marriage. At the time of the interview in 2010, Taylor was retired and had been a resident of Marcus Garvey Nursing Home for one year.
  In the interview, Robert Taylor goes over his many biographical details in a loose, vague timeline. He mentions military service and several jobs he had over his lifetime; the longest being with the New York City Transit Authority. It was during that time as a station porter, that he discovered a dead body on the platform. He reflects on the work his parents did and how they instilled a work ethic and values. Taylor talks about the difficulties of sharing his first cramped apartment, where he met the woman he went on to marry. He speaks of the move they made to Flatbush and how he witnessed the rising blight from drug traffic and shuttered businesses that changed Crown Heights. Taylor recalls learning about radio and television repair in the service, as well as how it felt to be drafted. He offers his sound advice to high school students and reflects on what he was like in his school days. Interview conducted by Alex Kelly.
  Basic training (Military education) |z United States; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nightclubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Nursing homes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Texas; United States |x Armed Forces; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; New York City Transit Authority; Taylor, Robert; United States. Army
- Taylor, Sarah, 2010 April 14; 2010.020.042
  Sarah Taylor was born in Estill, South Carolina in 1943. At age eight, she moved to Brooklyn with her family and initially lived in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood. Taylor has lived at a few Brooklyn addresses from childhood to adulthood, most prominently on Eastern Parkway, and in 1980, she moved to a home on St. Charles Place. She attended P.S. 44, 35 and 258, then Girls' High School, where she ran on the track team. Taylor's mother died while the young woman was still in high school, and taking a job became a greater priority than attending college. She first worked for the New York City Department of Social Services. After nine years, she left for a job with Shirley Chisholm's election campaign. She gave her time to The Muse museum in Brooklyn, and worked for many years at the Ford Foundation. She was retired as of 2010. She has been a leader of the Crow Hill Community Association for decades; taking the positions of Secretary, Vice President and a project manager.
  Sarah Taylor begins the interview with her admiration for the Crown Heights neighborhood and remembers the homes she has lived in for her fifty years in Brooklyn. She gives an overview of Crow Hill Community Association (CHCA), the origin of the name, inspiration for organizing, and speaks at length on the important work accomplished by the organization. Taylor addresses the question of where Weeksville and Crow Hill were located and names the present and previous directors of the Weeksville Heritage Society. She talks about that group's efforts to renovate and her turn as the "Weeksville Lady." Taylor reflects on meeting Eve Porter and the roles they created within CHCA. She remembers her childhood schools, homes and transportation; contrasting her South Carolina youth with her Brooklyn youth. She talks about the civil service, non-profit and volunteer work she's done outside of CHCA and closes with an appreciation of Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Floyya Richardson, Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; South Carolina; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crow Hill Community Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Girls' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Green, Roger L. (Roger Leon); Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History; Taylor, Sarah
- Weitz, Herbert, 2010 April 12; 2010.020.043
  Herbert "Herbie" Weitz was born into an upper class family in Brooklyn in 1934. His first home, on Washington Avenue and Eastern Parkway in Crown Heights, had a live-in maid and a visiting maid. By 1941, the family had moved to a home overlooking Ebbets Field and a short while later, to Union Street and Kingston Avenue. Weitz attended P.S. 167, Crown Heights Yeshiva, and Erasmus Hall High School. He delayed his graduation because of time spent at a notorious pool hall on Union and Kingston. After joining the army, Weitz managed an officers' club in Germany. He was a New York bartender until the early 1970s, when he took over his father's bookbinding and rare books shop, Weitz, Weitz and Coleman, on Lexington Avenue. By 2008, the binding business was renamed WMG Bookbinding and had moved to the Gravesend neighborhood of Brooklyn, and Weitz was commuting from Manhattan. He grew up as an only child and has no children.
  In the interview, Herbert "Herbie" Weitz clearly recollects the twelve years of his youth spent in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He talks about specific memories of the three houses in which he lived, including one that overlooked the Dodgers' ballpark, Ebbets Field. He reels off the schools he attended: P.S. 167, Crown Heights Yeshiva, and Erasmus Hall High School. Skipping classes in his junior year to shoot billiards at a neighborhood pool hall and interact with gangsters led to a short term period as a dropout. Weitz recalls the ethnic makeup of his block and when, in 1947, the first African American family moved in. He recalls the social life of Brooklynites; including nightclubs, gambling, movie theaters, stickball games and museums. Weitz revels in storytelling and reminisces about pool hustling, getting into physical fights with a friend and the many games he played at Lincoln Terrace Park. Interview conducted by Ansie Montilus, Monica Parfait, Quanaisha Phillips and Alex Kelly.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ebbets Field (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish religious education; Motion picture theaters |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z United States; Erasmus Hall High School; Saint Gregory's Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Weitz, Herbert